[Music]
hey everyone
so this is the latest film in our sense
making series
all about the problem of truth in the
digital age
so if the last couple of films were
about the failure of the traditional
media
this is about the alternative media the
hopes and the failure conditions of that
in particular this is about
how we split into warring tribes online
how that tribalism is enforced and what
we might be able to do about it
introducing some really interesting
frameworks and also talking about
mimetic mediation between the different
online tribes
and it's also about where some really
important things seem to be shifting
on the front lines of the culture war
and the biggest frame as i think i've
said before
is that i feel that we're in this
interregnum period between two worlds
we're seeing the accelerated collapse of
the existing structures
particularly the sense-making structures
but we don't yet have a decentralized
network solution to the problem of truth
you could imagine that we might have one
but right now we're in this kind of no
man's land
and if the previous films were really
about the the problems and the ongoing
accelerated collapse of the traditional
media
this is what are the failure conditions
of the alternative media
and is there anything that we might be
able to do about it
and hopefully there's a few signs of
hope in this film
so the first couple of films really
looked at the crisis in journalism
how it was increasingly being replaced
with activism
and ideological conformity so this is
going to look much more closely at the
alternative media the online media
and in a way the problem is worse there
because most online sites don't even
really aim for balance they don't really
aim for
showing both sides of the story and as
tristan harris explained in the recent
film that we put out
that's because the incentive structure
of the online world
actually selects for polarization
division and fixed ideas to get
attention within that
that sphere i have to use outrage so
both sides the left and the right are
using
outrage to get people to get to get
people's attention that's what causes
this kind of what we call the race to
the bottom of the brain stem
for attention so what it also selects
for is a type of interacting
that relies on ridicule it relies on
dunking
it relies on bad faith and bad faith is
something i'm going to come to in the
next
topic because i think we desperately
need a definition of what bad faith is
so it's not just a subjective judgment
that means i don't have to talk to this
person we don't have to talk to this
person
and we've covered the intellectual dark
web on this
program before quite a lot because it
was deliberately set up
to be a place beyond that polarization
spiral a place with
a certain type of good faith
argumentation i've also explained why i
think it
fell short of those aims and where it
got stuck
and turned into a bit of a tribalism
itself but why i was really excited
when the intellectual dark web was first
named in 2018
was i'd seen the collapse of journalism
accelerated by the digital
wave and this was the first kind of
emergent phenomenon that looked like it
might be trying to tackle the problem
the idea that someone like joe rogan
like sam harris
like dave rubin they had found a niche
outside the mainstream outside the
traditional media and they've become
very popular so it was a
it was a genuine emergent phenomenon
they'd sort of grown in the cracks
left by the mainstream media by the
traditional media but i think if we're
even going to start to deal with the
problem we have to understand what's
going on at a much deeper level
than just the surface conflict we need
to understand how for example the tech
platforms are leveraging the lower
angels of our nature
as tristan harris explained there's a
race to the bottom of the brain stem
looking for limbic hijack looking for
polarization looking for outrage
and it's not even in a way it's not the
tech platform's fault because they're in
an incentive structure where if they're
not doing it then one of their
competitors is going to do it
and ultimately what it's showing up is
that we are in a self-terminating system
the underlying dynamics that are leading
to the self-termination that people feel
and sense right now
are not different in kind than the ones
that we've been facing since the
beginning of what we call civilization
they're different in magnitude
and in the speed of process factoring
the exponential curves involved the tech
platforms are just magnifying a really
deep flaw with the source code of
society
rival risk dynamics multiplied by
exponential tech
self-terminate exponential tech is
inexorable we cannot put it away so
we either figure out anti-rivalry or we
go extinct the human experiment comes to
a completion
that's like that's the core thing
figuring out anti-rivalry
is a psycho-spiritual process inside of
ourselves
can we actually even get along with our
family members can we pay attention to
our
emotions and triggers that hijack us
from sovereignty because the moment i'm
getting pissed in my value system is not
to be an angry person i'm actually
hijacked
right can i pay attention to that and
actually
have some sovereignty over my own
interstate and how i show up in the
world and i think the really key piece
to understand what's going on
is venkatesh rouse the internet of beefs
where he describes how the incentive
structure of social media
has created a toxic landscape that is
not only
allowing bad behavior but actively
rewarding bad behavior
he explains in this how the internet has
been transformed into an online battle
zone
that he calls the internet of beefs a
beef only thinker is someone you cannot
simply talk to
anything that is not an expression of
pure unqualified support for whatever
they are doing or saying
is received as a mark of disrespect and
a provocation to conflict
from there you can only crash into
honour-based conflict mode
or back away and disengage online public
spaces are now being slowly taken over
by
beef only thinkers as the global culture
wars evolve into a stable
endemic background societal condition of
continuous conflict
as the great weirding morphs into the
perma-weird
the public internet is turning into the
internet of beefs
so twitter is absolutely core to this
battle it's where you can see the tribes
being formed
and enforced and policed in real time
and it has a huge effect on the stories
that are being covered by the
traditional media
as barry weiss said in her resignation
letter
twitter is not on the masthead of the
new york times
but twitter has become its ultimate
editor as the ethics of that platform
have become those of the paper
the paper itself has increasingly become
a kind of performance space
stories are chosen and told in a way to
satisfy the narrowest of audiences
rather than to allow a curious public to
read about the world
and then draw their own conclusions so
another really essential framework is
by peter limberg and conor barnes in
their culture war 2.0 paper
where they introduced the concept of
memetic tribes and listed a lot of the
different memetic tribes
memetic tribes you're probably familiar
with some of the names that are
active in the culture war whether it be
the social
justice activists black life matters
metoo alt-right manosphere we can even
say the new atheists or
rationalists post-rationalists street
epistemologists
any sort of world view that's sort of
defining what culture is
and and sort of imposing their view on
it
and we we created the spreadsheet where
we had a taxonomy this meta taxonomy
that had uh telos their their main
purpose
what what's their goal um existential
threat what are they most worried about
uh mental models how they how they view
the world
their sacred values what do they view
most important that if you transgress it
you'll trigger them
and i think you know trigger warning
applies to all mimetic tribes all
sort of worldviews and the idea is that
these mathematic tribes are all
combating with each other and all these
odd alliances are forming
and the overall theme of the piece was
that the old culture war which could
easily be split into left and right
was now fragmenting into a multipolar
war i think you can see that that a lot
of the most
intense conflicts are between people who
are theoretically on the same side
the example of barry weiss at the new
york times being a perfect example
i mean parry barry weiss was a liberal
would agree with
most things that other people in the new
york times would agree with
but they were split on this central
culture war issue of whether the woke
left had gone too far or not
and that was the central that was by far
the most heated division
there's conservative columnists at the
new york times they don't create
anywhere near as much heat as barry
weiss
received while she was there as she
explained in her
resignation letter the level of
animosity towards her was just extreme
so the key to understanding the
landscape of mimetic tribes is to
understand that each one
has some part of the truth they are all
often right about the certain part of
the map that they're looking at
but in a way it's like the blind man and
the elephant there's all these blind men
they're touching an elephant
and they view their point on the
elephant where they're touching either
the trunk or
or the tail as their reality
and what the good thing about that is is
that they're hyper focused on that area
they feel the texture they can smell it
and that affords them ability to see
things that we might not
otherwise see if we weren't touching
that spot but the problem is is that if
you just view
that spot as the entirety of reality
then you're in trouble you need to talk
to each other
the idea was an invitation to the reader
to look at it from a different
perspective
and i view this this this whole whole
white paper in memory tribes and the
frame that this is a multipolar almost
post-modern war
is sort of a psychoactive drug because
if you see
the mimetic tribe that you belong to
alongside all these other memetic tribes
that might jog you out of uh your belief
system just for a moment
and then he introduces this concept
which i think is absolutely central to
navigating this culture war
of mimetic mediation between the tribes
how do we mediate amongst all these
warring tribes
and i view memetic mediation as the hard
problem of culture war 2.0 but
there's things that we're experimenting
with in toronto called the anti-debate
where
it's sort of uh a gamification of
understanding
um there's conversational modalities
like empathy circles
where they apply carl rogers act of
listening
to a four-way conversation getting
people to
look at new sites meta news sites like
all sides that kind of shows the bias of
each
news platform on one issue so in the
last few months peter has actually set
up his own channel called the stower
where he'll be doing some of this
memetic mediation between the different
tribes
which i'll put in the show notes below
now one of the key issues in
any mediation which i know from my time
as a foreign affairs journalist
is that you are generally at most risk
from people on your own side when you
enter into mediation
it takes incredible bravery on the part
of someone who's high profile within a
certain tribe to go into mediation
anyway
and often you'll be accused of betrayal
by your own side before you'll be
attacked by the other side famous
examples
gandhi was killed by a hindu nationalist
because they thought you'd been too
accommodating to muslims
in israel yitzhak rabin was killed by an
orthodox israeli because they thought
he'd made too many concessions to the
palestinians
it really takes incredible bravery on
behalf of the people
who are involved in mediation they've
got to be of strong character
they've got to be willing to move in
their positions
they've got to be willing to be accused
of betrayal by the people on their side
this is not an easy thing and there's so
many human reasons that stop us doing it
including that we may have been sort of
profitably
associated with a certain position but i
think
some of that mediation between
high-profile
individuals in the internet of beefs
or who are willing to step away from the
internet of beefs
is going to be required if we're going
to get through the next
few years without widespread conflict
i promised you some signs of hope and
this is where i think things are
starting to move
in the alternative online world
matt taibi who i referenced before he
wrote the piece where he talked about
eight different revolts in different
newsrooms around
the us a longtime stalwart of the left
really experienced reporter at rolling
stone
her just went on so he's written a
series of pieces recently
including the left is the new right
where he's saying that the left has
become censorious the left has become
the thing that
he as someone who was part of a counter
culture rebelled against
now the left has become the centaurious
um
force which you may argue he's kind of
late to the party on that one but
he's saying that and he recently went on
brett weinstein's podcast
where he apologized to brett for not
seeing
what brett was talking about the dangers
of the radical left
i have the distinct pleasure of being
here with matt taibi who is a reporter
for rolling stone
and sub stack many of you will know him
for those who don't you should
definitely
look into his writings he has been
utterly
fantastic and consistent for decades on
some of the most difficult topics
that there are to report on i would say
he is a singular voice in journalism
today
welcome matt thank you so much for
having me on brett it's a it's an honor
um well i'm not quite sure where to
start i have to tell you
2020 is proving to be a remarkable year
and i think uh you and i are both seeing
a disturbing and complex
picture emerging and i suppose the thing
to do is just to figure out whether we
can make any useful
sense of it yeah i mean i
i think um the the first place for me
that that's interesting is
uh i think a lot of us in journalism um
are coming around slowly to the fact
that we we missed
some big stories that took place uh
on campuses a few years ago um
you know yours the obviously the one in
yale
uh but really you know we've heard from
academics
over the years about certain things that
were going on
and we i think the the reflexive
reaction among most people in the press
and most of us are kind of liberal
leaning
in our political orientation um
was to say okay well that's a right-wing
talking point
and you know we're gonna have trouble
selling that story anyway if we try to
do it
and so let's not even bother
and uh so there was a combination of not
taking it seriously and then there's a
little bit of like cancel culture
already working in
into the thought process with
journalists because we just knew that we
couldn't get that past editors
right um but now
you know this is this has come into our
business in a huge way
uh in particular in the last couple of
months as you know so
um you know people like me i think oh
people like you an apology
for coming around to this late if
anything
yeah well i have a uh a rule of thumb
when it comes to such things
which is i welcome anybody
without the need for an apology who
recognizes that they got it wrong
and says so my feeling is there's a
point at which
you didn't get it and this is true for
all of us and then there's a point at
which you do
and you know you didn't see it as close
up as
we did on campuses but anyway thank you
for acknowledging that there was
something to see
and that it it wasn't seen by you and
others early enough
and as predicted matt tybee is now being
attacked online by
a lot of people who used to support him
there's a couple of really interesting
tweets just a few
hours ago by glenn greenwald another
high-profile left-wing journalist
watching the in-group group think
beehive swarming by every twitter social
climber and online warrior
against matt taibi is amazing to behold
he's the same journalist you've admired
for two decades
as he mercilessly exposed the corrupt
financial system and war machine
he hasn't changed what's changed is you
your utter inability to tolerate even
slight deviations
from whatever orthodoxies your group
holds at that moment
all driven by social media which
converts every bit of descent
into an atrocity betrayal heresy
in group treason now greenwald is the
journalist who broke the edward snowden
story and was a co-founder of the
intercept
very controversial personally i disagree
with him about a lot of things
but he like matt taibi is prepared to go
against the crowd
to be disagreeable and ironically this
was one of the
supposed virtues of everyone in the
initial intellectual dark web
what's going on is that when you ask
any large collection of people to salute
a nonsensical flag and pledge allegiance
to it
and more or less everyone makes the
calculation
i guess if this is going to get me
through my day i'll salute any flag
then you've got the one gal or one guy
who doesn't want to
well my observation is that that person
is usually sitting on an entire
mountain of interesting thoughts that
they
don't have the freedom to simply make a
convenience
readjustment and so from that
perspective yeah
in general if you ask a thousand people
to salute a flag that makes no sense and
tell them that
they'll be incentivized you'll get a
thousand dollar check at the end or
you know you won't lose your job and
somebody stands up
and says no way i'm getting out of here
do what you want
that person is usually much more
interesting than just being a contrarian
that person is usually saying no because
they've got an entire world view
that is uh built by hand and and bespoke
and so that's why
this method of finding people has been
relatively fruitful it's
people who don't back down usually don't
back down for a reason because there's
every reason just to go along
and just a couple of days ago mata
iglesias who's one of the founders of
vox
one of the most woke publications out
there
uh recently signed the harper's letter
of on free speech
and then was criticized publicly by one
of
vox's employees who claimed that he was
the fact that he signed the letter was
making her unsafe
matt has just agreed to go on eric
weinstein's podcast
so i think this is the most important
front in the mimetic war that's being
waged at the moment
and it started to create a lot of very
strange alliances
but as i've said about the intellectual
dark web in the past it's really
important that it doesn't just become a
reactive
reactionary force against the radical
left that it actually pushes forward to
a vision and a new synthesis there was a
really interesting article in qualette
recently
about how it can't just be about
rejecting
wokeness those opposing it have to offer
a much more compelling
moral vision of the future so the last
framework i'm going to introduce and
link to in the show notes
is integral theory which i've talked
about before
ken wilber's integral theory which is
still
i think the best overall framework for
understanding what's going on
he wrote an amazing ebook after the
trump election called trump and a
post-truth world
how the leading edge of culture had
become totally dysfunctional
so in a way they'd been a control alt
delete to an earlier operating system of
tribalism
and integral is a really really good map
it feels like a number of the thought
leaders today and whether that's in
the crypto space and thinking about kind
of decentralized organizations or
whether it's in
existential risk or even kind of in more
sophisticated versions of
personal development and leadership
development i have noticed that even
without
teasing it out or calling it out it kind
of bubbles up in conversations that
a significant number of those folks
took on and can seriously considered
integral frameworks at some point
earlier in their life
not to be taken too seriously not to get
lost in the map
as jamie wheel said in the film that we
put out about the legacy of integral
best to learn it and forget it it
basically was like
crack for asperger's kids you know the
idea of getting a
contact high from reading ken stuff
and getting to see yourself on a map and
position yourself
up and away from no matter what the
disclaimers were and there were plenty
of disclaimers
the reality as that showed up in culture
and in practice
resulted in a bunch of dissociated
eggheads
masquerading as as jedi and
thinking that they could solve the world
from the position of a white board
so in the integral map we've got
different value systems given different
colors
and the orange value system of modernity
is what arrived with the scientific
revolution
a single perspective and
green is what fully arrived in the 1960s
which is
post-modernism or multiple perspectives
and the positive side of that was the
introduced things that were not seen
from the orange perspective
it introduced the voices of people who'd
been shut out of the conversation
and that was a really positive
development but what happened with green
and the danger of green and why it's
become so toxic
and effectively dysfunctional as a
system
was that it insisted that all there was
was multiple perspectives and that there
was no truth
so it'll maintain for example that
it is universally
undeniably true that there
is no universal truth
it will maintain that all knowledge is
social construction
it's all an interpretation it all
depends upon which culture
it's arising in and yet everything that
i just said
that represents the green point of view
it maintains that its view is not
culturally constructed
it's true for all people at all places
at all time
it's not a matter of interpretation it's
got real
truth nobody else has truth because
objective truth doesn't exist
but that view itself is held to be
objectively true by the postmodernists
so they do get caught up in this
enormous kind of contradiction so what
integral shows is that green has to
integrate orange values to be healthy
and
what it's actually been doing is
attacking orange values
green succeeded in the 60s because it
rested on orange values
it fought for free speech it insisted on
the rights of everyone to be heard
and that's what actually allowed the
green revolution in civil rights and
different areas of the culture to
succeed but what's going on at the
moment
is that green is now attacking denying
and shutting down free speech in too
many different areas
and that's effectively like it's soaring
off the branch that it's resting on
which is incredibly incredibly dangerous
we're seeing things like that playing
out in the culture for example
this tweet from the writer charles blow
arguing that it's okay for workplaces to
fire employees for their views
which only works if you assume that your
views are going to be dominant in the
workplace and they're only going to be
sacking
reprehensible bigots but it's also the
same justification that would allow
someone to be sacked for being
homosexual or being sacked for their
for their progressive views so it's a
completely short sight of perspective
and we're seeing genuine liberals who
went through the counter culture
realizing this
i'm going to end with matt taibbi
because he put out something absolutely
hilarious the other day at the beginning
of one of his podcasts on rolling stone
first of all i just want to make an
announcement i made a terrible mistake
and i'm hoping somebody out there can
help me
robin d'angelo is having an online
seminar this weekend
and i planned to attend
uh while on hallucinogens and i
bought all the drugs uh but was too late
in buying a ticket
uh which is also it's already closed so
if there's somebody out there who has a
ticket to this
july 18th all day robin d'angelo seminar
and is willing to sell i mean i'm
willing to pay almost any price frankly
uh so if you have a ticket to this thing
and are willing to give it to me
um i will i promise to eat a
dangerous quantity of drugs and
and attend that seminar uh this weekend
and uh and then write about later
which if anyone knows the um fear and
loathing in las vegas hunter s thompson
was the heart of psychedelic culture
taking loads of drugs and going to the
republican convention in las vegas
so matt is keeping a lie of the true
values of the psychedelic counterculture
the irreverence and subversion
because he understands in a way that i
think not enough
people on the left have yet understood
that someone like robin d'angelo
is nurse ratchet from one flew over the
cuckoo's nest
she's now the dominant force in the
culture a number one best seller
charging twelve thousand dollars for a
corporate consulting gig
enforcing conformity and compliance
thanks for watching i'd love to get some
suggestions for
mimetic mediation who are the people
that should be in dialogue with each
other that could be in dialogue with
each other
that could see each other's point of
view and could have a generative
conversation
because this is what we're going to come
to later in the series talking about
what a generative conversation looks
like
and also in the next film i'm going to
talk about bad faith
how it's kind of a very slippery concept
but it's a central
issue to deal with if we want to move
forward because it's very easy to use
that as a way of shutting down the
conversation
so thanks for watching and see you soon
rebel wisdom was set up to make sense of
the world
at a deeper level than the mainstream
media it was built for these times of
crisis and change
which is why we want to do what we can
to meet the challenge of the times
more films and also for our rebel wisdom
members
weekly sense making calls with our
amazing interviewees
and also we're introducing the wisdom
gym
a place to practice some of the skills
that we've talked about on the channel
thanks for watching and see you soon